<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Infinite regress - Reviews</title><link>https://miljko.org/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2019 17:12:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>The Making of the Atomic Bomb</title><link>https://miljko.org/the-making-of-the-atomic-bomb/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Fifty years and what feels like ten times as many people crammed into a story of physics, engineering, politics, psychology, diplomacy, and war. An awesome book about an awesome topic, and yes that’s how awesome was meant to be&amp;nbsp;used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the first half of the book, about the physics of it all, much more than the second. It has fewer characters, all of them characters, and has fewer parallel stories to tell. A whole chapter is devoted to a manuscript authorship dilemma: kudos to Rhodes for making it&amp;nbsp;interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Niels Bohr and Ernest Rutherford were some of those characters. So was Marie Curie: “How does it feel to be married to a genius, Mdm. Curie?” “I don’t know, ask my husband”.&amp;nbsp;Indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there’s anything that I got from the second half, about engineering and deploying the thing, it’s that large projects are messy, costly, and never completely satisfying. But that’s kind of a&amp;nbsp;given.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all the firebombing (Dresden et al), and two atomic bombs top it off, how much worse must have the Allies behaved for their atrocities to be equal to those of the Nazis? Note that Stalin was an&amp;nbsp;Ally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew little of Oppenheimer before reading this except that he got into political trouble after Los Alamos. The book doesn’t go there, but every mention of him foreshadows his troubles to come. Which would be very confusing if I knew absolutely nothing about him, and was still kind of confusing with the little knowledge I&amp;nbsp;had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soldiers were much more interesting to read about than politicians, and came out on top in almost every&amp;nbsp;confrontation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know what I wrote about the second half of the book, but the last three chapters are easily the best, and the way Rhodes covered the actual bombing of Hiroshima was&amp;nbsp;masterful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will probably be the best book I read this&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Richard Rhodes, &lt;i&gt;1986&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2019 17:12:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2019-04-02:/the-making-of-the-atomic-bomb/</guid></item><item><title>Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind</title><link>https://miljko.org/sapiens-a-brief-history-of-humankind/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A speedy overview of the past 70 some millennia of humanity. Self-aware without being modest about its proclamations. Very 2014 in its optimism to dread ratio, but with enough forewarning that things might slip at any moment that it doesn’t appear naïve when being read in 2019. A few&amp;nbsp;observations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The book’s main thesis is that civilization as we know it lies on many, many figments of our collective imagination: states, laws, human rights, religions, corporations, etc. The last hundred years have sped this up, pulling people  apart from families and other tangible local communities and into fictive constructs such as nations, sports teams, organized religion, and other forms of fandom. Are Twitter and Facebook communities more or less real than these, and if more, are they why people have been having a hard time suspending their&amp;nbsp;disbelief?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Many religions are poked, proded, and pulled apart by witty turns of phrase, but Harari turns dead serious whenever buddhism is discussed. Unlike christianity and islam, buddhism gets whole running paragraphs of in-depth explanation. &lt;a href="https://www.vox.com/2017/2/28/14745596/yuval-harari-sapiens-interview-meditation-ezra-klein"&gt;Did the book need a religious disclaimer&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;His go-to example for discussing nationalist myths is Serbia. It figures. Kudos for doing it&amp;nbsp;respectfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Another thesis is that capitalism lives by using up future resources in form of credit, which in turn produces and enlarges those very same future (now present) resources. In addition to being a very &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2397535/"&gt;Predestination&lt;/a&gt; way of seeing things, does that support or conflict with Tyler Cowen’s thesis in &lt;a href="http://miljko.org/eng/2018/10/20/stubborn-attachments/"&gt;Stubborn Attachments&lt;/a&gt; that we tend to — but shouldn’t — discount the future? Maybe we (or capitalists, at least) are at the same time optimists by thinking the future will be better by default, but also saying to hell with it by using those perceived future benefits now, to the detriment of future people? To this non-economist modern capitalism looks like an underbaked&amp;nbsp;ideology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;This is the best-looking and best-made soft cover edition of a non-fiction book I’ve ever&amp;nbsp;read. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Yuval Noah Harari, &lt;i&gt;2014&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2019 15:16:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2019-01-25:/sapiens-a-brief-history-of-humankind/</guid></item><item><title>Flashpoint: Trieste</title><link>https://miljko.org/flashpoint-trieste/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A history of the Trieste kerfuffle between Tito and the Allies immediately following &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WW2&lt;/span&gt;, but also an overview of the many warring sides: Non-soviet Allies, the Soviets, Tito’s partisans (“Yugoslavs” but also sometimes “Slovenians” and “Croats”), Chetniks (“Serbs”), Ustashe (“Croats”), Italian communists, Italian fascists, Italian non-communist non-fascist partisans, and let’s not forget the Nazis. Whew… At least the French are out of the&amp;nbsp;picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s biased towards the Americans and the British, but then that’s not surprising considering the author. All other sides being equally horrible — according to the book at least, and it’s a lazy though intellectually safe stance to make — it manages to be sort of objective but then in a lot of cases resorts to citing some not very objective secondary sources written in the background of a much bigger kerfuffle in the 1990s. Jennings is no Ron Chernow, and even less of a Robert Caro. The region needs someone of Cs’ tenacity and attention to detail to untangle even the footnotes of Balkan history like Trieste. I can’t imagine who would be able to tackle a Power Broker-like biography of Tito, but I’d be happy to read&amp;nbsp;one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Christian Jennings, &lt;i&gt;2017&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2019 21:38:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2019-01-12:/flashpoint-trieste/</guid></item><item><title>Titan: The Life of John D. Rockefeller, Sr.</title><link>https://miljko.org/titan-the-life-of-john-d-rockefeller-sr/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A biography of the Rockefeller patriarch. It’s a messy book, but then it was also a messy 97 year-long life. A few&amp;nbsp;highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt; He benefited from starting his business, unencumbered by monetary or ideological debt, just when one of the greatest technological leaps of human history occurred. What got him all that money was luck and ruthlessness more than business acumen (what others thought) and religious zeal/hand of God (what he thought). His subsequent mostly failed business ventures confirm&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Even so, it is his religion that led him to become the world’s greatest philanthropist, and also set up a template for modern billionaires on how to donate most of their fortune formally and on a grand scale. Yay for religion,&amp;nbsp;then?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Rockefeller’s company &lt;i&gt;Standard Oil&lt;/i&gt; and other trusts emerged at a time when legislature couldn’t keep up with rapidly evolving technologies; by the time laws caught up, it didn’t matter. Private data and human attention are 21st century&amp;nbsp;oil. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; You also have corrupt politicians, populist presidents, and progressive and gender/racially sensitive (dare I say woke) but ineffective intelligentsia. It all seems very&amp;nbsp;familiar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; A search for “John D Rockefeller” on youtube brings mostly conspiracy videos and hilarious reenactments. I did find &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=N0DuV1wpDhY"&gt;one video of the man himself&lt;/a&gt; in which he looks eerily like my&amp;nbsp;grandmother.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Ron Chernow, &lt;i&gt;2004&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 28 Dec 2018 14:42:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2018-12-28:/titan-the-life-of-john-d-rockefeller-sr/</guid></item><item><title>The drunkard’s walk: How randomness rules our lives</title><link>https://miljko.org/the-drunkards-walk-how-randomness-rules-our-lives/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;An introduction to the normal distribution and to our incompetence in dealing with probability. Since it covers a different type of probability than &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fooled_by_Randomness"&gt;“Fooled by randomness”&lt;/a&gt;, and only skims the heuristics and biases discussed at length in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking%2C_Fast_and_Slow"&gt;“Thinking, fast and slow”&lt;/a&gt;, it works well as a prologue to both books. This trio should be mandatory reading for premeds, by the way, with the rest of Taleb’s Incerto rounding out an advanced curriculum.  They would for sure have served me better than the anemic statistics textbooks I had to plough through in the early&amp;nbsp;‘00s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Leonard Mlodinow, &lt;i&gt;2009&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2018 11:37:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2018-11-28:/the-drunkards-walk-how-randomness-rules-our-lives/</guid></item><item><title>Buffet: The making of an American capitalist</title><link>https://miljko.org/buffet-the-making-of-an-american-capitalist/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’m glad the author, Roger Lowenstein, didn’t even attempt to appear impartial in this, Amazon’s most highly rated of Warren Buffett biographies. It’s the reverse of a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Power_Broker"&gt;Power Broker&lt;/a&gt; hit job: in the reprint afterword, Lowenstein is wistful about not getting more praise from Buffet while the aforementioned is signing the author’s personal copy at a conference. How wonderful it would be if our heroes loved us as much as we love&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granted, Buffet is an easy person to love, what with being an aw-shucks Midwestern pro-government regulation democrat who is modest, smart, and also one of the richest people in world. That he first earned his money off of America’s addiction to sugar and shopping, followed by tobacco and war, followed by decidedly inegalitarian buddy deals, all while neglecting his wife to the point of her leaving, and his children to the point of their becoming New Age musicians, just supports his claim to being the most American of all American heroes.&amp;nbsp;Kudos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Roger Lowenstein, &lt;i&gt;2008&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 27 Nov 2018 13:25:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2018-11-27:/buffet-the-making-of-an-american-capitalist/</guid></item><item><title>A Wrinkle in Time 👎</title><link>https://miljko.org/a-wrinkle-in-time/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;So much wasted potential in this one. It could have been a great movie for both children and adults, a Labyrinth for the age of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CGI&lt;/span&gt; and social justice. Instead, it’s a confused, hurried mess in which lots of Stuff happens for no good reason; a Michael Bay extravaganza for your middle-schooler. My daughter (6) liked it, but even she questioned a major plot point. “But, why did X become evil, daddy?” I’ve no idea, Honey, and I’m not sure the screenwriters gave it much thought&amp;nbsp;either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such is the faith of many book adaptations; this one even more so, having had to pass through the Disney committee wringer. I haven’t read the book(s? That’s how much I know about the potential franchise) but I’ve read and watched enough fantasy to know that 1) your made-up world needs to have rules, and 2) if you break them, it better be for a good reason. The few week rules set in the Wrinkle’s first half are promptly broken at the half-time, with no explanation and nothing to replace them. Instead you get a holodeck of a planet, where anything can happen: hurricane in a haunted forest turns into a Stepford wives cul-de-sac turns into a crowded beach, and no there is nothing connecting those&amp;nbsp;dots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is too bad — each one of those scenes would’ve made a good episode for the second season of the unmade Wrinkle &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; show, perfect for Disney’s new streaming service. Such a&amp;nbsp;waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Ava DuVernay, &lt;i&gt;2018&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 17:07:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2018-11-20:/a-wrinkle-in-time/</guid></item><item><title>Ending medical reversal</title><link>https://miljko.org/ending-medical-reversal/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The first thing I picked up after taking the hematology boards was this gem from Chicago&amp;#8217;s medical royalty (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/adamcifu"&gt;Adam Cifu&lt;/a&gt;) and everyone&amp;#8217;s favorite oncologist (this is of course a joke — you know that people hate your guts, &lt;a href="https://VPplenarysesh"&gt;Vinay&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#8217;t, and still don&amp;#8217;t, care much for the title. It is ambiguous: if medical reversal means overturning an established practice that was based on weak to no evidence once stronger evidence comes along — usually in the form of a (multi-center, blinded) randomized controlled trial — why on earth would you want to end reversals? Well, the book is about how to stop those kinds of practices from becoming established in the first place, which would indeed end medical reversal, but an easier way to stop them and one that would be endorsed by most of industry and many researches would be to just not look. &amp;#8220;Ending Medical Reversal the Hard Way&amp;#8221; is therefore a more appropriate&amp;nbsp;name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title aside, I agreed with pretty much everything they wrote, from reforming medical education, through stopping direct-to-consumer marketing and direct-to-academic (not their words) payments, to having more people participate in (simpler, cheaper, and fairer) randomized trials. I enjoyed their honesty and clear style, and wished my medical school had at least a passing resemblance to the one they proposed (if you thought &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; medical education leaned too much on basic science-oriented and was heavy in professorial mechanistic proclamations, try the average European med school). Granted, I work in a federal research hospital and focus on some of the rarest of the rare diseases; but that only makes me shake my head in disbelief more when my colleagues who specialize in breast or lung cancer, not to mention coronary artery disease and diabetes, randomize enormous numbers of patients to search for minute differences in surrogate&amp;nbsp;outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Vinayak Prasad and Adam Cifu, &lt;i&gt;2015&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2018 10:23:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2018-11-12:/ending-medical-reversal/</guid></item><item><title>Stubborn Attachments</title><link>https://miljko.org/stubborn-attachments/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This is as close to a &amp;#8220;Rules for Life&amp;#8221; book as we&amp;#8217;ll get from Tyler Cowen, and if you&amp;#8217;ve &lt;a href="http://www.conversationswithtyler.org"&gt;listened to his podcast&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://marginalrevolution.com"&gt;followed his blog&lt;/a&gt; what&amp;#8217;s inside won&amp;#8217;t surprise you — but it will make you think. Which is good: surprise is overrated anyway, and things that depend on it don&amp;#8217;t do well on re-reading/watching/listening. I&amp;#8217;ll be coming back to this&amp;nbsp;one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cowen argues that growth is good even when it doesn&amp;#8217;t benefit everyone all the time. There are things that can grow that you can&amp;#8217;t measure (like happiness, life satisfaction, health, culture, feeling of superiority [I may be misremembering some of these]), so don&amp;#8217;t focus on wealth only but instead on Wealth Plus. Also, distant future is just as important as the near future, so don&amp;#8217;t sacrifice long-term prospects for short-term gains. Speaking of future, we can&amp;#8217;t predict it, so even though tiny decisions can influence it in an oversized manner we should stop fretting over those and focus on the big picture: which is to chose policies that provide the greater sustained benefit sooner. Finally, common sense morality can usually steer you in the right direction, but if it feels like it&amp;#8217;s not, remember everything else in the book and you should be all&amp;nbsp;set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s all well and good, except that I kept imagining someone from Serbia — currently a second-world European kakistocracy — living by the standards of this book. Hilarity ensued: for things would be included in Wealth Plus that Cowen hadn&amp;#8217;t foreseen (the ability to redraw borders, to name one), and common sense morality would include good doses of nepotism, chauvinism, and the desire to cheat the state (yes, yes, I know,&amp;nbsp;#notallserbs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the first thing that&amp;#8217;s keeping this book from being great is that it can&amp;#8217;t be universally applied — it was written by an American for his fellow Americans who have lost their way — and doesn&amp;#8217;t explore, or even mention, the implications of his vague concepts of Wealth Plus and common sense morality being different around the&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is that shortly after admitting that economists don&amp;#8217;t have crystal balls (the twelve-year-old me would have loved to put parentheses around &amp;#8220;crystal&amp;#8221;), he goes on to compare hypothetical policies based on their projected rates of growth well into the future. It may be my lack of an economic background speaking, but how can those two go&amp;nbsp;together?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But do read the book. After my first pass I can say it&amp;#8217;s good, if not great. For me as a doctor the idea of delaying gratification for long-term gains felt familiar. The oncologist in me would add that inflicting harm for a known long-term benefit is also reasonable and depending on the alternatives even preferred. Of course, it took centuries of wading in the dark before medicine got to the point where it could with any certainty predict the outcome of its interventions. Are social sciences there&amp;nbsp;yet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Tyler Cowen, &lt;i&gt;2018&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 09:10:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2018-10-20:/stubborn-attachments/</guid></item><item><title>Applied minds: how engineers think</title><link>https://miljko.org/applied-minds-how-engineers-think/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I wanted to like this book more than I actually did. The title is seductive for those of us  who work with people’s very unengineered fleshy bits: would it help if we added some engineering tools to our mental toolbox? Well, maybe it would, but this book couldn’t help me find them, being more of an essay on &lt;i&gt;why&lt;/i&gt; I should think like an engineer rather than an instruction manual on &lt;i&gt;how&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, you need a lot anecdotes anecdotes to explain the Why; stories zip by so fast they gave me whiplash. There are too many narratives and not enough thoughts: instead of just buttressing the main point or two, the anecdotes take center stage, sprinkled with outlines of different ideas that never become&amp;nbsp;central.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a book about engineering, I expected better&amp;nbsp;construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Guru Madhavan, &lt;i&gt;2016&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2018 16:07:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2018-09-07:/applied-minds-how-engineers-think/</guid></item><item><title>If on a winter’s night a traveler</title><link>https://miljko.org/if-on-a-winters-night-a-traveler/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The book is almost forty years old but it could have been written yesterday. It is short, smart, punchy, and very, very meta. It also makes me want to learn Italian, though I understand William Weaver is a good&amp;nbsp;translator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Italo Calvino, &lt;i&gt;1981&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2018 18:02:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2018-04-15:/if-on-a-winters-night-a-traveler/</guid></item><item><title>The death and life of great American cities</title><link>https://miljko.org/the-death-and-life-of-great-american-cities/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Jane Jacobs loved Greenwich Village so much that she wrote a book about why that was and why more neighborhoods weren’t like it. She looked at other similar areas in Boston, Chicago, Philadelphia, etc. as well some failed ones, and gave a few guidelines on what was needed for safe, lively, and desirable city&amp;nbsp;streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has enough whimsical observations of city life to keep things interesting for its too-many—over 400—pages (e.g. on a city park’s homeless population: &lt;i&gt;Almost imperceptibly, like the hand of a clock, the raggle-taggle reception creeps around the circular pool at the center of the square. And indeed, it is the hand of a clock, for it is following the sun, staying in the warmth. &lt;/i&gt;Or, comparing a safe-but-dirty city street to a desired but decidedly unsafe park: &lt;i&gt;The sidewalks were dirty, they were too narrow for the demands put upon them, and they needed shade from the sun. But here was no scene of arson, mayhem or the flourishing of dangerous weapons. In the playground where the night-time murder had occurred, things were apparently back to normal too. Three small boys were setting fire under a wooden bench. Another was having his head beaten against the concrete. The custodian was absorbed in solemnly and slowly hauling down the American flag&lt;/i&gt;). It’s all quite&amp;nbsp;lovely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But ultimately, it is an exercise in confirmation bias that misses as many essential points as it reveals. What was arguably the most devastating influence on American cities — Robert Moses — is but a misguided elderly official who, and kudos to him, knows his way around public funds. City planners like big, disruptive projects because of their bad (deductive!) reasoning, not because they give politicians photogenic ribbon-cutting&amp;nbsp;ceremonies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to know why American cities are the way they are, better read &lt;i&gt;The Power Broker&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Jane Jacobs, &lt;i&gt;1961&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 18:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2018-01-24:/the-death-and-life-of-great-american-cities/</guid></item><item><title>The Last Jedi 👊</title><link>https://miljko.org/the-last-jedi/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Extraordinary set pieces strung together by the thinnest of plots, based on an absurd, sitcom-worthy failure to communicate. A particular subplot should have been spun off as a buddy cop&amp;nbsp;movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ray-Luke-Kylo triangle should have been a bigger part of the movie, but then many of the new characters, the ones that aren’t white and/or men, would have nothing to do. Such are the problems of building on an old and popular franchise: you can’t both stay true to the roots and change with the&amp;nbsp;times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has cute animals and looks good in 3D though, so Dora (5.4)&amp;nbsp;approves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Rian Johnson, &lt;i&gt;2017&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 10:16:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2018-01-08:/the-last-jedi/</guid></item><item><title>The hero with a thousand faces</title><link>https://miljko.org/the-hero-with-a-thousand-faces/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;What you do is you take as many fairy-tales and myths and other stories as you can — Campbell is extraordinarily good at collecting them — then squint and trace out the patterns. Us humans are very good at finding patterns where none exist (&lt;a href="http://www.popularmechanics.com/space/moon-mars/a17529/a-short-history-of-martian-canals-and-mars-fever/"&gt;just ask Percival Lowell&lt;/a&gt;), so it is no wonder that we end up with an overarching story, albeit disjointed, which is — of course it is — steeped in New Age &lt;a href="https://meaningness.com/monism"&gt;monism&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plot twist: unlike &lt;a href="http://digitalesammlungen.uni-weimar.de/viewer/image/PPN64011217X/1/#topDocAnchor"&gt;similar attempts in other arts&lt;/a&gt;, this one becomes wildly successful, serving as a template for other stories that end up following it more closely than any of the tales of old ever did (see &lt;a href="http://www.hbo.com/the-leftovers"&gt;Kevin Garvey’s literal and metaphorical travails&lt;/a&gt; for the most recent example). I like The Leftovers, so I would say The Hero… is a net benefit for the civilization. It just wasn’t for&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full disclosure: I stopped reading the book near the end of the first (of two) sections, the one about The Hero’s Journey. I therefore never got to the Cosmogonic cycle, and cannot comment. Do let me know if there was a surprise&amp;nbsp;ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Joseph Campbell, &lt;i&gt;2008&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 03:12:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-06-07:/the-hero-with-a-thousand-faces/</guid></item><item><title>50/50 👍</title><link>https://miljko.org/5050/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;An oncologist(?), a psychologist, and a surgeon give master classes on unprofessional behavior while treating &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JGL&lt;/span&gt; and his &lt;a href="http://theoncologist.alphamedpress.org/content/19/2/193.full"&gt;unfortunately named tumor&lt;/a&gt;. Even though only one of the three was meant to look bad in the movie, they each break a fundamental rule of the doctor-patient relationship: don’t be a douchebag, don’t sleep with the patient, don’t tell them everything will be fine when you have no clue. Cut out the profanities, and you’d have a semester’s worth of medical ethics&amp;nbsp;discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cut out the profanities, though, and you’ll miss half the movie. Seth Rogen — a dirty old man trapped inside Fozzy the Bear — does what he’s been doing &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g5iaHTkpTv0"&gt;ever since Judd Apatow found him&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/FNskZ6GQz2A"&gt;heart of gold included&lt;/a&gt;. Fortunately, 50/50 has better timing than anything to come out from the Apatow cringe factory, and even has a&amp;nbsp;point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical miscellanea: was the diagnosing physician a medical oncologist, neurologist, neurosurgeon, or an orthopedic surgeon? Likely not the first, else he wouldn’t give neoadjuvant cytarabine for a sarcoma, and probably not the latter two since another, overoptimistic &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MD&lt;/span&gt; does the actual surgery. Can a psychologist perform interviews for what she admits will be her PhD thesis without getting informed consent? How can a surgeon say with any certainty that “everything will be fine” minutes after performing what she admitted to be a difficult operation &lt;a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0360301698002235"&gt;for a tumor with a relapse rate north of 50%&lt;/a&gt;. You know, the 50% that gave the movie its&amp;nbsp;name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, thumbs&amp;nbsp;up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Jonathan Levine, &lt;i&gt;2011&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2017 16:36:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-05-06:/5050/</guid></item><item><title>Doctor Strange 👎</title><link>https://miljko.org/doctor-strange/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Inception for the Disney Franchise Age of American cinema. Trying to be deliberately inoffensive to a particular class of &lt;i&gt;consumer&lt;/i&gt;, it dodges &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_v2exWrsGOc"&gt;Mickeydom’s most glorious moments of cultural sensitivity&lt;/a&gt; only to fall on the sword of blandness. But credit where it is due — it takes talent to make a trippy 60s comic book that’s oddly relevant in &lt;a href="https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2017/03/14/maintaining-sanity-weird-timeline/"&gt;today’s world of magic mystery turmoil&lt;/a&gt; into a boring, predictable, dull, uninspired, yawn-inducing, delta wave-producing, paint-by-numbers origin&amp;nbsp;story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you thought only the Strange-ness was fumbled you must not be a doctor, because &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/bUi8Youavz8"&gt;his day job features the most laughable medicine this side of the Human Centipede&lt;/a&gt;. Though I shouldn’t complain too much — I imagine aerospace engineers cringe an order of magnitude more when watching any other Marvel&amp;nbsp;miracle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thumbs&amp;nbsp;down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Scott Derrickson, &lt;i&gt;2016&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2017 06:58:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-04-26:/doctor-strange/</guid></item><item><title>Black Swan 👍</title><link>https://miljko.org/black-swan/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Every ballet metaphor told and/or written by dancers, visualized: you don’t feel like a swan, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mCmY7Q8wwts"&gt;you become one&lt;/a&gt;; competitiveness means &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2jeq15Jw88M"&gt;murdering the competition&lt;/a&gt;; and liberating yourself from constraints is &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/zNPUsQYlSB0?t=1m48s"&gt;suicide&lt;/a&gt;. It is on the nose and at times painful to watch, but I would not expect anything else &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ADJE5gat_W8"&gt;from the master of the afterschool special&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portman is a pro: she gets you to swallow the banal white swan/black swan analogy whole, and ask for more, goes through every exercise in Aronofsky’s mental torture playbook like it’s nothing, and looks believably cool and composed until she believably isn’t. Watching her in this movie makes a certain trilogy an even bigger crime against&amp;nbsp;directing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thumbs&amp;nbsp;up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Darren Aronofsky, &lt;i&gt;2010&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2017 07:17:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-04-25:/black-swan/</guid></item><item><title>Stoker</title><link>https://miljko.org/stoker/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Derivative&amp;nbsp;drivel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Chan-wook Park, &lt;i&gt;2013&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2017 10:59:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-03-25:/stoker/</guid></item><item><title>La La Land</title><link>https://miljko.org/la-la-land/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A solid attempt in recreating &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/GB2yiIoEtXw"&gt;musical films of old&lt;/a&gt; that succeeds in all the technical details — the cuts are smoother, the camera livelier, the sets more real — but fails in a thing that matters more: &lt;a href="http://miljko.org/eng/2017/02/26/whiplash/"&gt;talent&lt;/a&gt;. Literally anyone (&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/jWEXGaupvlQ"&gt;yes, anyone&lt;/a&gt;) from the cast of Hamilton would have been a better choice for Bigeye’s partner. Heck, Justin Timberlake would have made more sense, being a human being of actual musical ability, and if you are forcing me to recommend &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/TA0VnUGu62o?t=11s"&gt;Curly&lt;/a&gt; for a role in your movie, your have miscalculated&amp;nbsp;horribly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way Gosling would possibly have made sense was if you were making a point that anyone could sing, but then don’t make the character a musician, and better don’t do that movie at all since &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/wjohhUyfCeY?list=PL2rnwFFQ-ThgnmoVYthu3TNVQ1SCrVEIb"&gt;it had already been done much better on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; 15 years ago&lt;/a&gt; by a man who &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/FTMuZSeSwIk"&gt;knows his musicals&lt;/a&gt;. And this is clearly not what Chazelle was trying to do, what with him incorporating &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/JpCLxnVpgbo"&gt;high-level bizarre dance numbers&lt;/a&gt; and movie-making subplots reminiscent of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Singin'_in_the_Rain"&gt;greatest American movie ever made&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emma Stone is a real jewel,&amp;nbsp;though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Damien Chazelle, &lt;i&gt;2016&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Mar 2017 18:49:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-03-23:/la-la-land/</guid></item><item><title>Birdman</title><link>https://miljko.org/birdman/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A faux-continuos shot of a washed-up superhero movie star trying to stage a Broadway comeback. The way it plays with space and time is admirable, and the law company of Keaton, Norton &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Stone does their job with perfection, but the subject matter is so far up Hollywood’s large intestine that &lt;i&gt;Birdman&lt;/i&gt; should best be compared to &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/15JsYSZIT-Q?t=1m3s"&gt;another well-known continuous shot&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is on-your-nose pretentious, and artsy by design, yet too loaded with contemporary references to become timeless. Its one deep message — the one about criticism — was &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/Ih6jcKd7VwU"&gt;much better stated, and with a more positive attitude, a decade ago in an animated film about a rat&lt;/a&gt;. Iñárritu must have made it on a&amp;nbsp;dare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Alejandro G. Iñárritu, &lt;i&gt;2014&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2017 16:54:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-03-14:/birdman/</guid></item><item><title>Hacksaw Ridge</title><link>https://miljko.org/hacksaw-ridge/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;An old-school paint-by-numbers war movie. &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3j3_iPskjxk"&gt;Each kind of scene in it has a bar that’s been set long ago&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h5p5j_K0CsY"&gt;and it doesn’t surpass any of them&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KxLFdJLSho8"&gt;Some are so high above it’s like they don’t exist&lt;/a&gt;. It does set some standards of its own, most notably for dehumanizing the enemy, who is never given more than 10 seconds of film at a time and always with &lt;a href="http://j387mediahistory.weebly.com/anti-japanese-propaganda-in-wwii.html"&gt;a growling face straight out of a propaganda poster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is a shame. The story of Desmond Doss as told in 2016 deserves better than a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WW2&lt;/span&gt; also-ran and &lt;a href="http://people.com/movies/the-true-story-of-hacksaw-ridge-and-desmond-doss-the-medal-of-honor-winner-who-never-fired-a-shot/"&gt;an illiterate journal article&lt;/a&gt;, for at least two reasons: he saved everyone he saw on the battlefield, American and Japanese; and no-one could get the number of people he helped straight, even as he was being given the Medal of Honor. Wondering how the other side thinks and feels, and sorting between truths, half-truths, and alt-truths are the themes of this decade, so it must have taken a lot of determination (or ignorance) on Braveheart’s part to ignore them so completely. Sort of like I’m ignoring Mel’s pet theme that wants to be central but can’t quite make&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PS&lt;/span&gt;: Spiderman Jr. does his best doing Jimmy Stuart doing a pious army medic, and almost makes it. Vince Vaughn makes a good drill sergeant. This is not a failure of&amp;nbsp;acting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Mel Gibson, &lt;i&gt;2016&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2017 07:07:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-03-07:/hacksaw-ridge/</guid></item><item><title>Kiss Kiss Bang Bang</title><link>https://miljko.org/kiss-kiss-bang-bang/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Neurotic burglar with a heart of gold meets neurotic gay private investigator for some neurotic fourth wall-breaking shenanigans. Ironman’s vintage post-rehab quips are supposed to be endearing, but turn the movie into an annoying &lt;i&gt;Ally McBeal&lt;/i&gt; spinoff that’s even less sure of itself. Val Kilmer’s misshapen botoxed head mumbles through most of the lines, &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/KgSkCewy-LU?t=2m10s"&gt;though his penis features in a memorable scene&lt;/a&gt;. There are many more gags that are just as good, but are connected by a not well thought-out metaphor (is it a home movie on a reel? on tape? is it just playing in Downey’s head?) to make a twisty-turney plot that’s meant not to be followed (not unlike this&amp;nbsp;sentence). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good thing Michele Monaghan is there to eat their lunch and make the movie&amp;nbsp;watchable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Shane Black, &lt;i&gt;2005&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 11:06:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-03-06:/kiss-kiss-bang-bang/</guid></item><item><title>Moonlight</title><link>https://miljko.org/moonlight/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A poem in three verses about introversion and grit that is also a story about a boy growing up black and gay and functionally parentless in a poor Florida neighborhood. Through symmetry, silence, and omission, that depressing premise — imagine having to be a teenager in Florida — never invokes depression. Compare and contrast to &lt;a href="http://miljko.org/eng/2017/02/23/manchester-by-the-sea/"&gt;sad tales of straight white lower-middle class woes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since issues of identity, gender, and race are somewhat of a thing in this early 21st century, the movie is also a Rorschach test for its audience. A thousand opinion pieces bloomed in its wake, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TPxAKQoKORI&amp;t=6s"&gt;few of which as deep as a single scene&lt;/a&gt;, yet quite a bit more pretentious. Thousands more are to come in liberal arts colleges across the country, and deservedly so — many films tend to induce sympathy and elation in one particular group of people, awkwardness and shame in another, and this one time those two groups have&amp;nbsp;flipped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Barry Jenkins, &lt;i&gt;2016&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 06:53:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-28:/moonlight/</guid></item><item><title>Whiplash</title><link>https://miljko.org/whiplash/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A.k.a. &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/S6vTI5g198E"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Whiplash: The Truth Behind the 10,000 Hour Rule&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Parker&amp;#8217;s a young kid, pretty good on the sax, gets up to play at a cutting session, and he fucks it up. And Jones nearly decapitates him for it. And he&amp;#8217;s laughed off stage. But the next morning, what does he do? He practices. And he practices, and he practices with one goal in mind: Never too be laughed at again. And a year later he goes back to the Reno and he steps up on that stage and he plays the best motherfucking solo the world has ever heard. So imagine if Jones just said &amp;#8220;Well, that&amp;#8217;s okay Charlie. That was alright. Good job.&amp;#8221; Then Charlie thinks to himself &amp;#8220;Well, shit. I did do a pretty good job.&amp;#8221; End of story. No Bird. That, to me, is an absolute tragedy. But that&amp;#8217;s just what the world wants now. People wonder why jazz is dying. I&amp;#8217;ll tell you, man - and every Starbucks &amp;#8220;jazz&amp;#8221; album just proves my point, really - there are no two words in the English language more harmful than &amp;#8220;good job”.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If delivering this dialogue gets you an award, how on Earth does writing it not also get you one? Never mind the precise shots, impeccable pace, &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/-Vb5G8xjc_0"&gt;midpoint that could have been a short movie on its own&lt;/a&gt;, and the adrenaline-surge-inducing ending that is musical, cinematic, and deeply philosophical all at once. Movies at their&amp;nbsp;best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Damien Chazelle, &lt;i&gt;2014&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 07:35:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-26:/whiplash/</guid></item><item><title>Arrival</title><link>https://miljko.org/arrival/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Flat characters cipher through a thinly plotted array of science fiction concepts which are new enough to the non-reading public to make the movie palatable on novelty alone. Since novelty may be the only thing that counts in what is bracketed as SciFi — &lt;a href="http://www.metacritic.com/movie/interstellar"&gt;look at &lt;i&gt;Interstellar&lt;/i&gt; being undeservedly panned&lt;/a&gt; — a movie whose emotional range begins and ends with a side plot of a dying child now has a shot at the Academy Award. Also, and it feels wrong to even have to write this, there are other ways to elicit emotion in your audience than killing off children, &lt;a href="http://miljko.org/eng/2017/02/23/manchester-by-the-sea/"&gt;dear movie-makers of 2016&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Respect where it is due: passing of Hawkeye as a plausible physicist — by having him not talk about physics the entire movie, but still — and floating the idea of world unification in anno domini 2017 are admirable feats. Not enough to offset the hours wasted on walking through a hallway and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLDzFnckanHQKM9BV3L8Msbx03OzdIu_78"&gt;80s-style montages&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Denis Villeneuve, &lt;i&gt;2016&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2017 08:13:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-25:/arrival/</guid></item><item><title>Manchester by the Sea</title><link>https://miljko.org/manchester-by-the-sea/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A dour movie about dour people living dour lives in a dour New England town. The camera is static and so are our hero’s faces. Long periods of voyeuristic shots of everyday life are punctuated by rare expressions of minimal emotion. Answers to all our questions are quickly revealed and dramatic tension never builds&amp;nbsp;up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That kind of direction is fine if you are &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/vGvDCmuDKKE"&gt;talking about a man’s mid-life crisis&lt;/a&gt;, but disturbing when your movie involves three children burning to death. Is seeing a couple of good acting performances worth subjecting yourself to emotional trauma that doesn’t result in a meaningful message (and anything on stoicism of the Irish can hardly count &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/JATICtPYGGI"&gt;if the Simpsons have already done it&lt;/a&gt;)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical things of note: &lt;i&gt;congestive heart failure&lt;/i&gt; is a diagnosis as broad as &lt;i&gt;lower back pain&lt;/i&gt; (i.e. not a real diagnosis at all); would anyone not work it up further, never mind that it is in an otherwise healthy 40-something; and do they not have ICDs in Manchester, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MA&lt;/span&gt;? &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/779blnz0JU8"&gt;Coach&lt;/a&gt; should not have died, least of all because without his death we wouldn’t have had this&amp;nbsp;movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Kenneth Lonergan, &lt;i&gt;2016&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 06:45:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-23:/manchester-by-the-sea/</guid></item><item><title>Looper</title><link>https://miljko.org/looper/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Although a movie that involves traveling through time, Looper is hardly a time-travel movie. Bruce Willis says as much when he brushes off any attempts to discuss the mechanics, implications, paradoxes, etc. for reasons of expediency. So, &lt;a href="https://www.xkcd.com/657/"&gt;Primer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://5by5.tv/b2w/204"&gt;Predestination&lt;/a&gt;, or even Back to the Future &lt;span class="caps"&gt;II&lt;/span&gt; this ain’t. Groundhog Day is more like it, only with shotguns, telekinesis, and a far messier&amp;nbsp;ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s unfortunate for me, since I prefer pure time-travel movies; and there isn’t enough — or any, really — Bill Murray in Looper to justify comparing it to that other category. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JGL&lt;/span&gt; spends too much time pretending to be Willis, who in turn phones it in. Elevator/hallway action scenes are good, but don’t come close to &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eRBwvIX7Sao"&gt;the peak of the genre&lt;/a&gt; (or even &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/cSUsBzE-Wuo"&gt;the western take&lt;/a&gt;, which was fundamentally a feature-length interpretation of that one scene from&amp;nbsp;Oldboy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, in fact, nothing new to see here, and the movie feels as flat as the Kansas plain it is set in. The one interesting thing about it is that, in what is the complete opposite of &lt;a href="http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/21/brick/"&gt;the director’s previous movie&lt;/a&gt;, Looper might be better appreciated in a&amp;nbsp;vacuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Rian Johnson, &lt;i&gt;2012&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2017 15:53:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-19:/looper/</guid></item><item><title>The Dark Forest</title><link>https://miljko.org/the-dark-forest/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Starts several years after &lt;a href="http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/18/the-three-body-problem/"&gt;The Three Body Problem&lt;/a&gt; and ends 200 years later, shortly after the first (brief, horrific) physical contact with alien technology. The future’s clean, white, Apple-y aesthetic was annoying enough for me not to feel too badly after it imploded, and the humans of the future were just as grating, but I assume that was one of the big points Liu wanted to make (that we are more closely related temporally than we are geographically or genetically, that is, not that &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/ydkvO6C9pTs"&gt;Jony Ive is a future-human&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another point: a book about humanity’s impending demise has a good quarter of it dedicated to one man’s delusions about art and love. Those passages end up being directly relevant to the plot, but if anything, &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/OVCxJ1aT24A"&gt;that takes away from them&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the character who ends up being the book’s main proponent of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Poverty_of_Historicism"&gt;historicism&lt;/a&gt; dies in the best standoff &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K4GAQtGtd_0"&gt;since the Gotham prisoners’ dilemma&lt;/a&gt;, which ends up being only the second-best of the many standoffs the book presents. It is a beautiful, self-referential standoff&amp;nbsp;heaven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Cixin Liu, &lt;i&gt;2015&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 07:04:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-15:/the-dark-forest/</guid></item><item><title>Miss Peregrine’s Home for Peculiar Children</title><link>https://miljko.org/miss-peregrines-home-for-peculiar-children/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Stylized but not &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/cEVilNDXd0A?t=54s"&gt;psychedelic&lt;/a&gt;, quirky but not &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/rAbAd4QBL1s"&gt;disturbing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/lqTLETOYkQg?t=1m30s"&gt;borrowed liberally from The Prisoner of Azkaban&lt;/a&gt; but with good effect. It’s one of Tim Burton’s better Tim Burton&amp;nbsp;movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, yes, the plot has holes, and some of the characters’ motivations are… peculiar (har har). The more important thing is this: after seeing it, &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/V_fOn_aWCNk"&gt;Dora wanted to fly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Tim Burton, &lt;i&gt;2016&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 08:53:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-12:/miss-peregrines-home-for-peculiar-children/</guid></item><item><title>While We’re Young</title><link>https://miljko.org/while-were-young/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The title fools you into thinking the movie’s central conflict is between youth and old age. Turns out, the generation gap is only a setup for the real fight — that of &lt;a href="http://www.ribbonfarm.com/2016/09/01/the-origin-of-authenticity-in-the-breakdown-of-the-illusion-of-the-real/"&gt;authentic versus fake&lt;/a&gt;.  It culminates with (old, authentic) Ben Stiller neurotically rollerblading into Lincoln Center, hoping for a catharsis after he reveals to his documentary film-making giant of a father-in-law that (young, fake) Kylo Ren based parts of his own documentary on&amp;nbsp;alt-facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Things change”, replies &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/character/ch0499002/?ref_=ttfc_fc_cl_t21"&gt;Mr. Breitbart&lt;/a&gt;, minutes after giving a speech on honesty in filmmaking. “Different things matter&amp;nbsp;now.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sadly prescient moment in a sadly prescient&amp;nbsp;movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Noah Baumbach, &lt;i&gt;2014&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2017 07:27:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-11:/while-were-young/</guid></item><item><title>Begin Again</title><link>https://miljko.org/begin-again/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Keira Knightly pulls off the sweater-wearing, guitar-wielding singer-songwriter nicely. Adam Levin doesn’t pull off acting — good thing none was needed for his cipher of a character. &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3cePV6R91j4"&gt;Kathleen Keener&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OFe39cg2dbY"&gt;Mark Ruffalo&lt;/a&gt; reprise their roles from every other movie they&amp;nbsp;made. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fluffy, predictable,&amp;nbsp;forgettable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;John Carney, &lt;i&gt;2013&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 07:21:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-07:/begin-again/</guid></item><item><title>Captain Fantastic</title><link>https://miljko.org/captain-fantastic/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;Little Miss Sunshine&lt;/i&gt; of the twenty-teens is a wet dream for a certain kind of liberal: a family that is smart, good-looking, self-reliant, and self-aware; in which the eight-year-old knows both the content and the significance of the Bill of Rights, and the eighteen-year-old has his pick of Ivy League schools but chooses to go to Namibia; in which a &lt;i&gt;Lolita&lt;/i&gt;-reading teenager unironically asks what is Coca-Cola, and gets &lt;i&gt;poison water&lt;/i&gt; as an answer; in which the fireside homeschool-assigned reading session (&lt;i&gt;Guns, Germs, and Steel&lt;/i&gt;; &lt;i&gt;Brothers Karamazov&lt;/i&gt;; &lt;i&gt;The Fabric of the Cosmos&lt;/i&gt;) breaks for a family drum&amp;nbsp;circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, mom kills herself while hospitalized for depression far away in New Mexico, a road trip ensues, thoughts, feelings, and inadequacies of their lifestyle are exposed. The setup is better than the second act, during which 1) the captain of the freshly single-parent household is predictably un-fantastic, and 2) the middle-crassness of his extended family is blown out of all proportion. The payoff is better — if nothing else, it will make its &lt;a href="https://silverbirchpress.wordpress.com/2013/05/11/pick-up-lines-new-yorker-cartoon-by-frank-modell/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;New Yorker&lt;/i&gt;-reading audience&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/07/19/t-magazine/entertainment/viggo-mortensen-captain-fantastic-reading-list.html?_r=0"&gt;Vigo Mortensen was, apparently, destined to be in this movie.&lt;/a&gt; The question is: wouldn’t it have been better — and truer to its message — as a&amp;nbsp;book?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Matt Ross, &lt;i&gt;2016&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 07:26:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-29:/captain-fantastic/</guid></item><item><title>How to write a thesis</title><link>https://miljko.org/how-to-write-a-thesis/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Umberto Eco’s rules and advice on how Italian university students of modest means should choose a relevant topic, conduct and organize research with limited resources, and format their final undergraduate thesis. Though created by and for someone in the humanities, much of it applies to all sciences — and the parts that don’t are at least&amp;nbsp;entertaining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was written in 1977, revised in 1985, and revised again when translated to English for both cultural and temporal/technological adjustments. &lt;a href="http://diplomski-rad-kako-napisati.blogspot.rs"&gt;A translation to Serbian (which is, amazingly, freely available online)&lt;/a&gt; needed neither, as &lt;a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/family-fiefdoms-blamed-for-tainting-italian-universities-2089120.html"&gt;Serbia and Italy have similarly dysfunctional systems of higher education&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a book whose most important section is the one on taking notes and organizing research, this edition has remarkably small margins and tight binding. No matter — it will feature prominently in the Acknowledgments section of my PhD thesis, if and when I finish&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Umberto Eco, &lt;i&gt;1977&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2017 17:33:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-28:/how-to-write-a-thesis/</guid></item><item><title>They Came Together</title><link>https://miljko.org/they-came-together/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The difference between loving homage and gross parody can be subtle, and what the movie ends up being usually depends on whether the author(s) actually like the genre they are spoofing. It is an easy guess, for example, that Edgar Wright likes &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WVsL9tUJLHs"&gt;zombie apocalypses&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PH-CvYpoSUo"&gt;buddy cop movies&lt;/a&gt;, or that Joss Whedon is &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ufF5p8VBsVk&amp;index=8&amp;list=PLZbXA4lyCtqo7ZL09v0c2VLxvak-8uUaR"&gt;into horror films&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people who made this thing must truly hate romantic comedies. It doesn’t wink at &lt;a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/RomanticComedy"&gt;rom-com tropes&lt;/a&gt; — it &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Sqb85Gfj0Fw&amp;index=4&amp;list=PLZbXA4lyCtqpFIO718l2rS3eypRgtgLPh"&gt;blows them out of all proportion&lt;/a&gt;, the acting is even cheesier, camera work blander. I could pick out clips for these, but its’s the entire movie. Moreover, the comedies it references are dated, going with &lt;i&gt;When Harry Met Sally&lt;/i&gt; (1989), &lt;i&gt;You’ve Got Mail &lt;/i&gt;(1998), and &lt;i&gt;Notting Hill&lt;/i&gt; (1999) over the more recent and even more ridiculous &lt;i&gt;Love Actually&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1K45RdE2qlk"&gt;interconnected plot&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h_dt27_0vL4"&gt;wannabes&lt;/a&gt;. And &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Pd-MpXCMcIs"&gt;the jokes are just too obvious&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making fun of something &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=Every+Romantic+Comedy+Ever"&gt;that is easy to make fun of&lt;/a&gt; is easy. Making a good movie that is also a parody is hard. &lt;i&gt;They Came Together&lt;/i&gt; (ha ha) is a decent&amp;nbsp;parody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;David Wain, &lt;i&gt;2014&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 06:35:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-26:/they-came-together/</guid></item><item><title>The Autopsy of Jane Doe</title><link>https://miljko.org/the-autopsy-of-jane-doe/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A haunted house movie where the house has a morgue in the basement (&lt;a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/the-real-csi-americas-patchwork-system-of-death-investigation"&gt;America is weird&lt;/a&gt;) and the ghost is lying on a stainless steel cart, all peaceful and symmetrical until a father-son team of coroners begins slicing into her. Roose Bolton is again to blame, in a way, but has more sense at the end of this one while leaving room for a sequel (The Autopsy 2: Richmond Horror, a working title that I just made up, so you can stop googling&amp;nbsp;it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a nice—if short—ride that would be much scarier for those who never attended an autopsy, but between the pacing, the acting, and the near-absence of &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=I8znuHwF490"&gt;jump scares&lt;/a&gt;, it’s the best horror movie I’ve seen since &lt;i&gt;It follows&lt;/i&gt;. It gets extra points for being truer to the genre—&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ietK_lZyDNY"&gt;no hipster soundtracks here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And no, you can’t put a think chunk of freshly brain under a microscope and see cells, much less figure out if a neuron is alive just by looking at it for 1.5 seconds. &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A9dw9BweRQk"&gt;Brian Cox can sell anything&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;André Øvredal, &lt;i&gt;2016&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 06:51:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-23:/the-autopsy-of-jane-doe/</guid></item><item><title>Brick</title><link>https://miljko.org/brick/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Twenty-somethings here are playing SoCal high-schoolers who &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vsv0WkFTiUw"&gt;talk like they are on the set of The Maltese Falcon&lt;/a&gt;; but it’s not &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VJmroCp_qa0"&gt;Bugsy Malone&lt;/a&gt; with a slightly older cast, and it’s not sort-of-like &lt;i&gt;film noir&lt;/i&gt;, either. This &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; a &lt;i&gt;film noir&lt;/i&gt;, complete with a Gordian knot of a plot, gritty textures half-concealed in darkness, and telegraphed archetypes (the loner, the vamp, the &lt;i&gt;femme fatale&lt;/i&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The teenagers seem parentless—save for a comic relief scene or two featuring the mom of our archetypal kingpin serving the boys cookies and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OJ&lt;/span&gt;—and the few other adults in the world treat them as equals. Clearly a fantasy, but you will have suspended your disbelief long before&amp;nbsp;then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It fares well when compared to the competition—but then, most of it had been made in the 1940s, so I wouldn’t call it &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IDyFh0x_ygM"&gt;a fair fight&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Rian Johnson, &lt;i&gt;2005&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 08:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-21:/brick/</guid></item><item><title>An Education</title><link>https://miljko.org/an-education/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The Worst Father in the World, here played by Alfred Molina, prefers wedding off his smart and ambitious underaged daughter (&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cwdbLu_x0gY"&gt;Sally Sparrow&lt;/a&gt;, 24 going on 16) to a 30-something con artist of means (&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TeWxZN1oVzA"&gt;a smirking Skarsgard&lt;/a&gt;), rather than financing her studying English at Oxford. It is the 1960s—why waste money on tuition if her only reason for attending university is to find a good&amp;nbsp;husband?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She likes his opera-champaign-trips-to-Paris lifestyle, he likes that she speaks French and looks at him like a God, so it looks like a win-win-win as she abandons high school for an engagement ring. But if you hang around scammers you will get scammed, and soon she learns he has a wife, a son, and countless past &lt;i&gt;jeunes femmes&lt;/i&gt; like her, some of whom ended up with child. A &lt;i&gt;deus ex machina&lt;/i&gt; in the form of an English teacher does help her get into Oxford, and she lives long and well enough to be able to write &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Education-Lynn-Barber/dp/1934633852/"&gt;the memoire that Nick Hornby turned into this screenplay&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a masterpiece, but serviceable as educational material for preteens. I hope Dora will grow up not to be as impressionable to&amp;nbsp;sleazeballs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Lone Scherfig, &lt;i&gt;2009&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 11:38:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-19:/an-education/</guid></item><item><title>The Three Body Problem</title><link>https://miljko.org/the-three-body-problem/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Written by an engineer, and reads like it. It uses a broad brush—with not much description or characterization—to explore such trivialities as life, reality, human perception, and humanity’s place in the&amp;nbsp;universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of it has a sense of odd turning into familiar: the bloodshed of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cultural_Revolution"&gt;the Chinese Cultural Revolution&lt;/a&gt; projected onto the book’s pro-alien human factions and real world’s &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occupy_movement"&gt;opposed&lt;/a&gt;-&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tea_Party_movement"&gt;yet&lt;/a&gt;-&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_Lives_Matter"&gt;alike&lt;/a&gt; movements; virtual realities inside a nesting doll of x-dimensional spaces &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GZgBcRhGPqs"&gt;that may themselves be virtual&lt;/a&gt;; environmental dangers, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electromagnetic_hypersensitivity"&gt;imagined&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_warming"&gt;real&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.pitt.edu/~jdnorton/papers/Chasing_final.pdf"&gt;Einstein supposedly pictured himself chasing a beam of light&lt;/a&gt; before developing his theories of relativity. Liu imagined standing on the surface of a planet quite unlike Earth to come to this book and its two siblings. Based on the first installment, I can tell that investing some time in the trilogy will be worth&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Cixin Liu, &lt;i&gt;2012&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 15:20:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-18:/the-three-body-problem/</guid></item><item><title>Children of Men</title><link>https://miljko.org/children-of-men/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Children of Men&lt;/i&gt; has aged well. Too well. Between Brexit, Zika, islamist fundamentalists, and police brutality, 2017 is much closer to the version of 2027 the movie portrays than what Cuaron could possibly have imagined while writing and directing&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brilliant long tracking shots include &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QfBSncUspBk"&gt;Juliane Moore’s bloody demise in a post-apocalyptic British mini-car&lt;/a&gt;, and Clive Owen’s &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=twcKoAQ7HIg"&gt;race through a desolate seaside town-slash-rebellious refugee camp&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YBzWTIexszQ"&gt;find the only baby alive on Earth&lt;/a&gt;. A lot of the movie could now be described as &lt;a href="https://www.twitch.tv/sneakysnackhobo/v/115812094"&gt;a Twitch video&lt;/a&gt;, though back then first-person shooters were &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IE46AFOqrC8"&gt;decidedly less realistic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this were Interstellar, Owen would have lived through the end and be reunited with a resurrected Moore. Fortunately, it is&amp;nbsp;not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Alfonso Cuaron, &lt;i&gt;2006&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 14:41:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-18:/children-of-men/</guid></item></channel></rss>