<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Infinite regress</title><link>http://miljko.org/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 06:45:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Manchester by the Sea</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/02/23/manchester-by-the-sea/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A dour movie about dour people living dour lives in a dour New England town. The camera is static and so are our hero’s faces. Long periods of voyeuristic shots of everyday life are punctuated by rare expressions of minimal emotion. Answers to all our questions are quickly revealed and dramatic tension never builds&amp;nbsp;up. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That kind of direction is fine if you are &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/vGvDCmuDKKE"&gt;talking about a man’s mid-life crisis&lt;/a&gt;, but disturbing when your movie involves three children burning to death. Is seeing a couple of good acting performances worth subjecting yourself to emotional trauma that doesn’t result in a meaningful message (and anything on stoicism of the Irish can hardly count &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/JATICtPYGGI"&gt;if the Simpsons have already done it&lt;/a&gt;)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical things of note: &lt;i&gt;congestive heart failure&lt;/i&gt; is a diagnosis as broad as &lt;i&gt;lower back pain&lt;/i&gt; (i.e. not a real diagnosis at all); would anyone not work it up further, never mind that it is in an otherwise healthy 40-something; and do they not have ICDs in Manchester, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MA&lt;/span&gt;? &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/779blnz0JU8"&gt;Coach&lt;/a&gt; should not have died, least of all because without his death we wouldn’t have had this&amp;nbsp;movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Kenneth Lonergan, &lt;i&gt;2016&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 06:45:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-23:eng/2017/02/23/manchester-by-the-sea/</guid></item><item><title>Looper</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/02/19/looper/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Although a movie that involves traveling through time, Looper is hardly a time-travel movie. Bruce Willis says as much when he brushes off any attempts to discuss the mechanics, implications, paradoxes, etc. for reasons of expediency. So, &lt;a href="https://www.xkcd.com/657/"&gt;Primer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://5by5.tv/b2w/204"&gt;Predestination&lt;/a&gt;, or even Back to the Future &lt;span class="caps"&gt;II&lt;/span&gt; this ain’t. Groundhog Day is more like it, only with shotguns, telekinesis, and a far messier&amp;nbsp;ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s unfortunate for me, since I prefer pure time-travel movies; and there isn’t enough — or any, really — Bill Murray in Looper to justify comparing it to that other category. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JGL&lt;/span&gt; spends too much time pretending to be Willis, who in turn phones it in. Elevator/hallway action scenes are good, but don’t come close to &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eRBwvIX7Sao"&gt;the peak of the genre&lt;/a&gt; (or even &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/cSUsBzE-Wuo"&gt;the western take&lt;/a&gt;, which was fundamentally a feature-length interpretation of that one scene from&amp;nbsp;Oldboy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, in fact, nothing new to see here, and the movie feels as flat as the Kansas plain it is set in. The one interesting thing about it is that, in what is the complete opposite of &lt;a href="http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/21/brick/"&gt;the director’s previous movie&lt;/a&gt;, Looper might be better appreciated in a&amp;nbsp;vacuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Rian Johnson, &lt;i&gt;2012&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2017 15:53:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-19:eng/2017/02/19/looper/</guid></item><item><title>The Dark Forest</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/02/15/the-dark-forest/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Starts several years after &lt;a href="http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/18/the-three-body-problem/"&gt;The Three Body Problem&lt;/a&gt; and ends 200 years later, shortly after the first (brief, horrific) physical contact with alien technology. The future’s clean, white, Apple-y aesthetic was annoying enough for me not to feel too badly after it imploded, and the humans of the future were just as grating, but I assume that was one of the big points Liu wanted to make (that we are more closely related temporally than we are geographically or genetically, that is, not that &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/ydkvO6C9pTs"&gt;Jony Ive is a future-human&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another point: a book about humanity’s impending demise has a good quarter of it dedicated to one man’s delusions about art and love. Those passages end up being directly relevant to the plot, but if anything, &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/OVCxJ1aT24A"&gt;that takes away from them&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the character who ends up being the book’s main proponent of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Poverty_of_Historicism"&gt;historicism&lt;/a&gt; dies in the best standoff &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K4GAQtGtd_0"&gt;since the Gotham prisoners’ dilemma&lt;/a&gt;, which ends up being only the second-best of the many standoffs the book presents. It is a beautiful, self-referential standoff&amp;nbsp;heaven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Cixin Liu, &lt;i&gt;2015&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 07:04:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-15:eng/2017/02/15/the-dark-forest/</guid></item><item><title>Miss Peregrine’s Home for Peculiar Children</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/02/12/miss-peregrines-home-for-peculiar-children/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Stylized but not &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/cEVilNDXd0A?t=54s"&gt;psychedelic&lt;/a&gt;, quirky but not &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/rAbAd4QBL1s"&gt;disturbing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/lqTLETOYkQg?t=1m30s"&gt;borrowed liberally from The Prisoner of Azkaban&lt;/a&gt; but with good effect. It’s one of Tim Burton’s better Tim Burton&amp;nbsp;movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, yes, the plot has holes, and some of the characters’ motivations are… peculiar (har har). The more important thing is this: after seeing it, &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/V_fOn_aWCNk"&gt;Dora wanted to fly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Tim Burton, &lt;i&gt;2016&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 08:53:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-12:eng/2017/02/12/miss-peregrines-home-for-peculiar-children/</guid></item><item><title>While We’re Young</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/02/11/while-were-young/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The title fools you into thinking the movie’s central conflict is between youth and old age. Turns out, the generation gap is only a setup for the real fight — that of &lt;a href="http://www.ribbonfarm.com/2016/09/01/the-origin-of-authenticity-in-the-breakdown-of-the-illusion-of-the-real/"&gt;authentic versus fake&lt;/a&gt;.  It culminates with (old, authentic) Ben Stiller neurotically rollerblading into Lincoln Center, hoping for a catharsis after he reveals to his documentary film-making giant of a father-in-law that (young, fake) Kylo Ren based parts of his own documentary on&amp;nbsp;alt-facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Things change”, replies &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/character/ch0499002/?ref_=ttfc_fc_cl_t21"&gt;Mr. Breitbart&lt;/a&gt;, minutes after giving a speech on honesty in filmmaking. “Different things matter&amp;nbsp;now.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sadly prescient moment in a sadly prescient&amp;nbsp;movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Noah Baumbach, &lt;i&gt;2014&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2017 07:27:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-11:eng/2017/02/11/while-were-young/</guid></item><item><title>Begin Again</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/02/07/begin-again/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Keira Knightly pulls off the sweater-wearing, guitar-wielding singer-songwriter nicely. Adam Levin doesn’t pull off acting — good thing none was needed for his cipher of a character. &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3cePV6R91j4"&gt;Kathleen Keener&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OFe39cg2dbY"&gt;Mark Ruffalo&lt;/a&gt; reprise their roles from every other movie they&amp;nbsp;made. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fluffy, predictable,&amp;nbsp;forgettable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;John Carney, &lt;i&gt;2013&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 07:21:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-02-07:eng/2017/02/07/begin-again/</guid></item><item><title>Captain Fantastic</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/29/captain-fantastic/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;Little Miss Sunshine&lt;/i&gt; of the twenty-teens is a wet dream for a certain kind of liberal: a family that is smart, good-looking, self-reliant, and self-aware; in which the eight-year-old knows both the content and the significance of the Bill of Rights, and the eighteen-year-old has his pick of Ivy League schools but chooses to go to Namibia; in which a &lt;i&gt;Lolita&lt;/i&gt;-reading teenager unironically asks what is Coca-Cola, and gets &lt;i&gt;poison water&lt;/i&gt; as an answer; in which the fireside homeschool-assigned reading session (&lt;i&gt;Guns, Germs, and Steel&lt;/i&gt;; &lt;i&gt;Brothers Karamazov&lt;/i&gt;; &lt;i&gt;The Fabric of the Cosmos&lt;/i&gt;) breaks for a family drum&amp;nbsp;circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, mom kills herself while hospitalized for depression far away in New Mexico, a road trip ensues, thoughts, feelings, and inadequacies of their lifestyle are exposed. The setup is better than the second act, during which 1) the captain of the freshly single-parent household is predictably un-fantastic, and 2) the middle-crassness of his extended family is blown out of all proportion. The payoff is better — if nothing else, it will make its &lt;a href="https://silverbirchpress.wordpress.com/2013/05/11/pick-up-lines-new-yorker-cartoon-by-frank-modell/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;New Yorker&lt;/i&gt;-reading audience&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/07/19/t-magazine/entertainment/viggo-mortensen-captain-fantastic-reading-list.html?_r=0"&gt;Vigo Mortensen was, apparently, destined to be in this movie.&lt;/a&gt; The question is: wouldn’t it have been better — and truer to its message — as a&amp;nbsp;book?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Matt Ross, &lt;i&gt;2016&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 07:26:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-29:eng/2017/01/29/captain-fantastic/</guid></item><item><title>How to write a thesis</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/28/how-to-write-a-thesis/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Umberto Eco’s rules and advice on how Italian university students of modest means should choose a relevant topic, conduct and organize research with limited resources, and format their final undergraduate thesis. Though created by and for someone in the humanities, much of it applies to all sciences — and the parts that don’t are at least&amp;nbsp;entertaining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was written in 1977, revised in 1985, and revised again when translated to English for both cultural and temporal/technological adjustments. &lt;a href="http://diplomski-rad-kako-napisati.blogspot.rs"&gt;A translation to Serbian (which is, amazingly, freely available online)&lt;/a&gt; needed neither, as &lt;a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/family-fiefdoms-blamed-for-tainting-italian-universities-2089120.html"&gt;Serbia and Italy have similarly dysfunctional systems of higher education&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a book whose most important section is the one on taking notes and organizing research, this edition has remarkably small margins and tight binding. No matter — it will feature prominently in the Acknowledgments section of my PhD thesis, if and when I finish&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Umberto Eco, &lt;i&gt;1977&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2017 17:33:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-28:eng/2017/01/28/how-to-write-a-thesis/</guid></item><item><title>They Came Together</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/26/they-came-together/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The difference between loving homage and gross parody can be subtle, and what the movie ends up being usually depends on whether the author(s) actually like the genre they are spoofing. It is an easy guess, for example, that Edgar Wright likes &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WVsL9tUJLHs"&gt;zombie apocalypses&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PH-CvYpoSUo"&gt;buddy cop movies&lt;/a&gt;, or that Joss Whedon is &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ufF5p8VBsVk&amp;index=8&amp;list=PLZbXA4lyCtqo7ZL09v0c2VLxvak-8uUaR"&gt;into horror films&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people who made this thing must truly hate romantic comedies. It doesn’t wink at &lt;a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/RomanticComedy"&gt;rom-com tropes&lt;/a&gt; — it &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Sqb85Gfj0Fw&amp;index=4&amp;list=PLZbXA4lyCtqpFIO718l2rS3eypRgtgLPh"&gt;blows them out of all proportion&lt;/a&gt;, the acting is even cheesier, camera work blander. I could pick out clips for these, but its’s the entire movie. Moreover, the comedies it references are dated, going with &lt;i&gt;When Harry Met Sally&lt;/i&gt; (1989), &lt;i&gt;You’ve Got Mail &lt;/i&gt;(1998), and &lt;i&gt;Notting Hill&lt;/i&gt; (1999) over the more recent and even more ridiculous &lt;i&gt;Love Actually&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1K45RdE2qlk"&gt;interconnected plot&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h_dt27_0vL4"&gt;wannabes&lt;/a&gt;. And &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Pd-MpXCMcIs"&gt;the jokes are just too obvious&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making fun of something &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=Every+Romantic+Comedy+Ever"&gt;that is easy to make fun of&lt;/a&gt; is easy. Making a good movie that is also a parody is hard. &lt;i&gt;They Came Together&lt;/i&gt; (ha ha) is a decent&amp;nbsp;parody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;David Wain, &lt;i&gt;2014&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 06:35:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-26:eng/2017/01/26/they-came-together/</guid></item><item><title>The Autopsy of Jane Doe</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/23/the-autopsy-of-jane-doe/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A haunted house movie where the house has a morgue in the basement (&lt;a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/the-real-csi-americas-patchwork-system-of-death-investigation"&gt;America is weird&lt;/a&gt;) and the ghost is lying on a stainless steel cart, all peaceful and symmetrical until a father-son team of coroners begins slicing into her. Roose Bolton is again to blame, in a way, but has more sense at the end of this one while leaving room for a sequel (The Autopsy 2: Richmond Horror, a working title that I just made up, so you can stop googling&amp;nbsp;it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a nice—if short—ride that would be much scarier for those who never attended an autopsy, but between the pacing, the acting, and the near-absence of &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=I8znuHwF490"&gt;jump scares&lt;/a&gt;, it’s the best horror movie I’ve seen since &lt;i&gt;It follows&lt;/i&gt;. It gets extra points for being truer to the genre—&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ietK_lZyDNY"&gt;no hipster soundtracks here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And no, you can’t put a think chunk of freshly brain under a microscope and see cells, much less figure out if a neuron is alive just by looking at it for 1.5 seconds. &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A9dw9BweRQk"&gt;Brian Cox can sell anything&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;André Øvredal, &lt;i&gt;2016&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 06:51:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-23:eng/2017/01/23/the-autopsy-of-jane-doe/</guid></item><item><title>Brick</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/21/brick/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Twenty-somethings here are playing SoCal high-schoolers who &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vsv0WkFTiUw"&gt;talk like they are on the set of The Maltese Falcon&lt;/a&gt;; but it’s not &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VJmroCp_qa0"&gt;Bugsy Malone&lt;/a&gt; with a slightly older cast, and it’s not sort-of-like &lt;i&gt;film noir&lt;/i&gt;, either. This &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; a &lt;i&gt;film noir&lt;/i&gt;, complete with a Gordian knot of a plot, gritty textures half-concealed in darkness, and telegraphed archetypes (the loner, the vamp, the &lt;i&gt;femme fatale&lt;/i&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The teenagers seem parentless—save for a comic relief scene or two featuring the mom of our archetypal kingpin serving the boys cookies and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OJ&lt;/span&gt;—and the few other adults in the world treat them as equals. Clearly a fantasy, but you will have suspended your disbelief long before&amp;nbsp;then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It fares well when compared to the competition—but then, most of it had been made in the 1940s, so I wouldn’t call it &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IDyFh0x_ygM"&gt;a fair fight&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Rian Johnson, &lt;i&gt;2005&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 08:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-21:eng/2017/01/21/brick/</guid></item><item><title>An Education</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/19/an-education/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The Worst Father in the World, here played by Alfred Molina, prefers wedding off his smart and ambitious underaged daughter (&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cwdbLu_x0gY"&gt;Sally Sparrow&lt;/a&gt;, 24 going on 16) to a 30-something con artist of means (&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TeWxZN1oVzA"&gt;a smirking Skarsgard&lt;/a&gt;), rather than financing her studying English at Oxford. It is the 1960s—why waste money on tuition if her only reason for attending university is to find a good&amp;nbsp;husband?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She likes his opera-champaign-trips-to-Paris lifestyle, he likes that she speaks French and looks at him like a God, so it looks like a win-win-win as she abandons high school for an engagement ring. But if you hang around scammers you will get scammed, and soon she learns he has a wife, a son, and countless past &lt;i&gt;jeunes femmes&lt;/i&gt; like her, some of whom ended up with child. A &lt;i&gt;deus ex machina&lt;/i&gt; in the form of an English teacher does help her get into Oxford, and she lives long and well enough to be able to write &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Education-Lynn-Barber/dp/1934633852/"&gt;the memoire that Nick Hornby turned into this screenplay&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a masterpiece, but serviceable as educational material for preteens. I hope Dora will grow up not to be as impressionable to&amp;nbsp;sleazeballs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Lone Scherfig, &lt;i&gt;2009&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 11:38:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-19:eng/2017/01/19/an-education/</guid></item><item><title>The Three Body Problem</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/18/the-three-body-problem/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Written by an engineer, and reads like it. It uses a broad brush—with not much description or characterization—to explore such trivialities as life, reality, human perception, and humanity’s place in the&amp;nbsp;universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of it has a sense of odd turning into familiar: the bloodshed of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cultural_Revolution"&gt;the Chinese Cultural Revolution&lt;/a&gt; projected onto the book’s pro-alien human factions and real world’s &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occupy_movement"&gt;opposed&lt;/a&gt;-&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tea_Party_movement"&gt;yet&lt;/a&gt;-&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_Lives_Matter"&gt;alike&lt;/a&gt; movements; virtual realities inside a nesting doll of x-dimensional spaces &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GZgBcRhGPqs"&gt;that may themselves be virtual&lt;/a&gt;; environmental dangers, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electromagnetic_hypersensitivity"&gt;imagined&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_warming"&gt;real&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.pitt.edu/~jdnorton/papers/Chasing_final.pdf"&gt;Einstein supposedly pictured himself chasing a beam of light&lt;/a&gt; before developing his theories of relativity. Liu imagined standing on the surface of a planet quite unlike Earth to come to this book and its two siblings. Based on the first installment, I can tell that investing some time in the trilogy will be worth&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Cixin Liu, &lt;i&gt;2012&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 15:20:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-18:eng/2017/01/18/the-three-body-problem/</guid></item><item><title>Children of Men</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/18/children-of-men/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Children of Men&lt;/i&gt; has aged well. Too well. Between Brexit, Zika, islamist fundamentalists, and police brutality, 2017 is much closer to the version of 2027 the movie portrays than what Cuaron could possibly have imagined while writing and directing&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brilliant long tracking shots include &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QfBSncUspBk"&gt;Juliane Moore’s bloody demise in a post-apocalyptic British mini-car&lt;/a&gt;, and Clive Owen’s &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=twcKoAQ7HIg"&gt;race through a desolate seaside town-slash-rebellious refugee camp&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YBzWTIexszQ"&gt;find the only baby alive on Earth&lt;/a&gt;. A lot of the movie could now be described as &lt;a href="https://www.twitch.tv/sneakysnackhobo/v/115812094"&gt;a Twitch video&lt;/a&gt;, though back then first-person shooters were &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IE46AFOqrC8"&gt;decidedly less realistic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this were Interstellar, Owen would have lived through the end and be reunited with a resurrected Moore. Fortunately, it is&amp;nbsp;not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Alfonso Cuaron, &lt;i&gt;2006&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 14:41:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-18:eng/2017/01/18/children-of-men/</guid></item></channel></rss>