<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Infinite regress</title><link>http://miljko.org/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 11:38:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>An Education</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/19/an-education/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The Worst Father in the World, here played by Alfred Molina, prefers wedding off his smart and ambitious underaged daughter (&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cwdbLu_x0gY"&gt;Sally Sparrow&lt;/a&gt;, 24 going on 16) to a 30-something con artist of means (&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TeWxZN1oVzA"&gt;a smirking Skarsgard&lt;/a&gt;), rather than financing her studying English at Oxford. It is the 1960s&amp;#x2014;why waste money on tuition if her only reason for attending university is to find a good&amp;nbsp;husband?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She likes his opera-champaign-trips-to-Paris lifestyle, he likes that she speaks French and looks at him like a God, so it looks like a win-win-win as she abandons high school for an engagement ring. But if you hang around scammers you will get scammed, and soon she learns he has a wife, a son, and countless past &lt;i&gt;jeunes femmes&lt;/i&gt; like her, some of whom ended up with child. A &lt;i&gt;deus ex machina&lt;/i&gt; in the form of an English teacher does help her get into Oxford, and she lives long and well enough to be able to write &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Education-Lynn-Barber/dp/1934633852/"&gt;the memoire that Nick Hornby turned into this screenplay&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a masterpiece, but serviceable as educational material for preteens. I hope Dora will grow up not to be as impressionable to&amp;nbsp;sleazeballs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Lone Scherfig, &lt;i&gt;2009&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 11:38:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-19:eng/2017/01/19/an-education/</guid></item><item><title>The Three Body Problem</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/18/the-three-body-problem/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Written by an engineer, and reads like it. It uses a broad brush&amp;#x2014;with not much description or characterization&amp;#x2014;to explore such trivialities as life, reality, human perception, and humanity&amp;#x2019;s place in the&amp;nbsp;universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of it has a sense of odd turning into familiar: the bloodshed of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cultural_Revolution"&gt;the Chinese Cultural Revolution&lt;/a&gt; projected onto the book&amp;#x2019;s pro-alien human factions and real world&amp;#x2019;s &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occupy_movement"&gt;opposed&lt;/a&gt;-&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tea_Party_movement"&gt;yet&lt;/a&gt;-&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_Lives_Matter"&gt;alike&lt;/a&gt; movements; virtual realities inside a nesting doll of x-dimensional spaces &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GZgBcRhGPqs"&gt;that may themselves be virtual&lt;/a&gt;; environmental dangers, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electromagnetic_hypersensitivity"&gt;imagined&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_warming"&gt;real&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.pitt.edu/~jdnorton/papers/Chasing_final.pdf"&gt;Einstein supposedly pictured himself chasing a beam of light&lt;/a&gt; before developing his theories of relativity. Liu imagined standing on the surface of a planet quite unlike Earth to come to this book and its two siblings. Based on the first installment, I can tell that investing some time in the trilogy will be worth&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Written by &lt;/i&gt;Cixin Liu, &lt;i&gt;2012&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 15:20:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-18:eng/2017/01/18/the-three-body-problem/</guid></item><item><title>Children of Men</title><link>http://miljko.org/eng/2017/01/18/children-of-men/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Children of Men&lt;/i&gt; has aged well. Too well. Between Brexit, Zika, islamist fundamentalists, and police brutality, 2017 is much closer to the version of 2027 the movie portrays than what Cuaron could possibly have imagined while writing and directing&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brilliant long tracking shots include &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QfBSncUspBk"&gt;Juliane Moore&amp;#x2019;s bloody demise in a post-apocalyptic British mini-car&lt;/a&gt;, and Clive Owen&amp;#x2019;s &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=twcKoAQ7HIg"&gt;race through a desolate seaside town-slash-rebellious refugee camp&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YBzWTIexszQ"&gt;find the only baby alive on Earth&lt;/a&gt;. A lot of the movie could now be described as &lt;a href="https://www.twitch.tv/sneakysnackhobo/v/115812094"&gt;a Twitch video&lt;/a&gt;, though back then first-person shooters were &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IE46AFOqrC8"&gt;decidedly less realistic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this were Interstellar, Owen would have lived through the end and be reunited with a resurrected Moore. Fortunately, it is&amp;nbsp;not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Directed by &lt;/i&gt;Alfonso Cuaron, &lt;i&gt;2006&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Miloš Miljković</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 14:41:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:miljko.org,2017-01-18:eng/2017/01/18/children-of-men/</guid></item></channel></rss>